TATIKA ANDERSON, BUSINESS SYSTEMS ANALYST

973- NJ | linkedin.com/in/tatikaanderson/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly skilled and driven Business Systems Analyst with over a decade of success evaluating and implementing banking and financial solutions. Track record of leading cross-functional teams to deliver cards, digital banking, payments technology, lending, fraud prevention, and AML initiatives which have resulted in 100% traceability to client requirements, \$3B revenue growth, and tactical fraud prevention and compliance features to reduce company exposure.

Skilled in:

- Business & Systems Analysis
- Collaboration & Stakeholder Engagement
- Software Testing & Validation (QAT, UAT, PIV)
- Communication Verbal, Written & Presentation
- Requirements Gathering & Documentation
- Problem Analysis & Process Improvement
- Data & Database Analysis, Mapping & Reporting
- Agile & Waterfall Methodologies

IIBA Certified Capable Business Analyst (CCBA®), currently pursuing CBAP® certification.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

CONSULTANT, BUSINESS SYSTEMS ANALYSIS

05/2021 - 01/2024

Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce (CIBC), Ontario Canada

Solution/Business BA Lead for multiple, medium to complex and cross-functional cards, digital banking, payments, fraud and enterprise authentication projects.

- Partnered with business and technology stakeholders to define and document business and/or solution requirements packages backlog, sprints, user stories, acceptance criteria, business rules, and use cases.
- Designed mockups, current and future state process flows, and traceability matrices.
- Collaborated with Product Owners, Sponsors, Architects and Developers to ensure alignment of solution with standards, enterprise strategy, and risk management. SME support to QA/UAT, PIV, and defect resolution
- Designed and drove BA plan and requirements, earning shared ownership with stakeholders & project success.

Notable Achievements:

- o <u>Authentication Transformation Ph 1 BRD:</u> Delivered 145 approved stories (Jira) in required 2 months.
- o <u>CIBC \$3B Costco Canada credit card portfolio acquisition:</u> Managed PIV, Delivered solution requirements.
- o <u>Future Dated & Recurring e-Transfers:</u> Solution secured distinction of 1st Canadian bank to enable this feature.
- o Extend Fraud TelAgent BP Reversal Window: Tactical solution to reduce suspicious Bill Payment transactions.
- <u>CAMLR (Ph 2) RBSS:</u> Delivered 100% compliance in AML reporting for assigned portfolio (Payments).
- Moment Makers: Multiple Purpose awards and consistently exceeded annual performance goals (2022-2023).

QUALITY ASSURANCE ANALYST (CO-OP)

05/2019 - 08/2020

Ontario Ministry of Education, Canada

Collaborated with lead BA and development teams to ensure requirements are correctly implemented.

- Identified gaps in test planning and proposed improvements to ensure solution quality.
- Created test scripts and data scenarios, executed test cycles against plan, performed code review for accessibility testing, and managed JIRA tickets and HP-QC defects.

Notable Achievements:

Reduced defects by 95% by aligning test results with business & software quality requirements.

SENIOR SYSTEMS ANALYST **SYSTEMS ANALYST**

07/2008 - 08/2017 04/2006 - 06/2008

National Housing Trust (NHT), Jamaica

Spearheaded business analysis for medium to large/complex and strategic multi-government agency projects, impacting up to ~1M customers, as well as internal staff and partnering agencies.

- Collaborated cross-functionally to define solution requirements & designs.
- Developed custom in-house solutions, including system integrations with Fiserv's Signature.
- Participated in Fiserv-driven ICBS upgrade to Signature and Alliant Branch Teller (ABT) preconditioning of objects, deployment of changes for core banking modules.
- Conducted deep-dive SQL queries to support QAT, solution implementation, production issues, and ad-hoc client requests/reports across the various lines of business and Signature subsystems/modules.

Notable Achievements:

- Tax Administration Modernization program Single Employer Annual Tax Return (S02): 75% reduction in employer tax filing effort, 90% improvement in Tax Compliance transparency across 4 tax agencies, automated secure retrieval & integration of the required Tax dataset with NHT's systems.
- o Fully Automated back end NHT Refund 3-tiered-approval & direct deposit payment workflow: Reduction in Refund processing times by 55% and eliminated staff embezzlement through implementation of robust access and monitoring controls.
- O Senior Director's award: "Excellent Customer Service"

BUSINESS ANALYST

07/2003 - 03/2006

National Housing Trust (NHT), Jamaica

- Implemented online NHT Contribution Refund application system replacing paper-based application process.
- Led the data analysis and implementation of business rules to standardize and merge customer records and corresponding accounts data - data analysis and rules validation (SQL), requirements, procedures/standards.
- Spearheaded outsourcing of the origination process for the Joint Financed loan product to partnering financial agencies/clients – defined policy, procedures, user manuals, facilitated training, and post-implementation support.
- Defined and executed QA test plans for in-house/outsourced solutions or core banking system customizations.
- Supported UAT, post-implementation verification (PIV), and defects resolution/troubleshooting.

Notable Achievements:

- o <u>Online Refund applications:</u> 75% reduction in staff & related costs, reduction in refund processing time.
- o <u>CIF Merger & Data Quality</u>: Reduced annual COTS licensing cost by ~50% due to removal of duplicate records and standardization procedures.
- Joint Financed Mortgage (JFM) product: Reduced NHT loan payout times by 75% with new product.

EDUCATION CERTIFICATIONS &

Certified Business Analysis Professional (CBAP®) - IIBA

In progress

Certified Capable Business Analyst (CCBA®) – IIBA

04/2021

Advanced (3-yr) Diploma, Computer Programming & Analysis – Seneca College, Canada

05/2018 - 12/2020

Certificate, Computer Studies – University of Technology, Jamaica

09/2003 - 11/2004

@gmail.com | , NJ | linkedin.com/in/tatikaanderson/